All right. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Happy איסרו חג. Isru Chag. Today's
דף daf is ט, Tes, but we pick up in the middle
of ח עמוד ב. Ches amud beis.
And this גמרא Gemara will be considerably easier than previous ones. I
keep on telling you that. I don't know if it's
borne out. Anyway, let's take a look. Second wide line. איזהו בתולה?
Eizehu besula? כל שלא ראתה. Kol shelo ra'asa. So now we're dealing
about the four women that the rabbis say would be concerned about
the moment they've seen onward, not back 24 hours, because they're בתולה
קטנים, besula ketanim, they're assumed to not be, you know, not be
likely to be seeing, they're a state where you assume they won't
be menstruating, and the first one of those is a young woman,
a young girl who has never had her period in her life.
כל שלא ראתה. Kol shelo ra'asa. So let's take a look at
the גמרא, Gemara, third wide line. תנו רבנן. Tana rabbanan. We've taught
in the ברייתא, baraita, נישאת וראתה דם מחמת נישואין, nisais vera'asa dam
machmas nisuin, if she married and she actually bled as a result
of the marriage, meaning it was hymenal bleeding, so obviously that's not
yet menstrual bleeding. That's not significant. ילדה וראתה דם מחמת לידה, Yalda
vera'asa dam machmas leida, or she had child, she gave birth to
a child and she saw blood in the process of childbirth, still
not hymeno. Of course the problem is as we know, it's possible
for a woman to be pregnant without ever having had her period,
that she got, the child was conceived with the very first time
she was having her period, so she never bled but she actually
conceived and then gave birth.
That's possible. But nevertheless for the גמרא, Gemara, because she has yet
to actually see a blood from her period, she is still not
considered in the category of a woman who is bleeding, and therefore
who is getting her period. And therefore the next time, the first
time she actually gets hymenal bleeding, it will only be the day
she see, the moment she sees, not backwards 24 hours. Okay, so
she gave birth because of
childbirth, עדיין היא נקראה לה בתולה. adayin hi nikra la besula. I
still call her a בתולה. besula. Here meaning literally virgin, but meaning
a woman who has yet to have her period. שבתולה שאמרו, she-besula
she-amru, because when they said בתולה, besula, בתולת דמים, besulas damim, it
does not mean a virgin, it means a woman who has never
bled.
ולא בתולת בתולים, lo besulas besulim,
and not a virgin from the hymenal virgin. So it's not a
classic virgin, it's a virgin who's never bled, that's this relevant category,
and therefore even if she's had sex, even if she's had childbirth,
if she's never bled she's in this category. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, איני, Aini, is that really true? ואמר רב כהנא, Ve'amar
Rav Kahana, תנא ג' בתולות הן, tana gimmel besulos hein, we've saw
that there were in a ברייתא, baraita, it says תוספתא Tosefta actually,
that there are three things that are referred to בתולה, besula, virgin.
What are they? בתולת אדם, Besulas adam, a human, a woman can
be a virgin.
בתולת קרקע, Besulas karka, virgin earth, right? We have that phrase even
today, right today, virgin virgin earth.
בתולת שקמה, Besulas shikma, and a virgin שקמה, shikma, which is a
type of a tree. I don't know what type of a tree
it is. I'm sure your English says Sycamore. Sycamore. Okay, well that
actually somewhat sounds like the word. Anyway, let's see what the significance
of this are. בתולת אדם, Besulas adam, so a person, a woman
who's a virgin, what's that definition? כל זמן שלא ניבעלה, Kol zman
shelo nivala, means she's never had sex. נפקא מינה, Nafka mina, the
relevance of this is לכהן גדול. leKohen Gadol. א כהן גדול A
Kohen Gadol has to marry a בתולה, besula, right? So it means
a woman who's never had sex. אי נמי, Ina nami, לכתובת מאתיים,
lekesuvas masayim, for all of מסכת כתובות Masechet Kesuvos or the first
half at least, it's all about a woman who if she's married
assumed to be a virgin, so her כתובה kesuvah is 200 זוז.
zuz. If it's she's known to not be a virgin or it
turns out she's not a virgin, then her כתובה kesuvah is only
100 זוז. zuz. And there the relevant definition is a woman who's
never had sex. Now of course an interesting question here, hello, an
interesting question here, which I am not going to answer, is what
about a woman who has had sex but is still a virgin
in terms of non-ruptured hymen? Like who has had anal sex or
who has had sex but it's not, does not rupture the hymen.
Right, so to what... Welcome,
welcome. You came at the right time.
So so this here the definition here is, it says not that
the בתולים besulim is in place, not that the hymen is unruptured,
but it says the relevance being for the definition being not have
had sex. But that's interesting, meaning I'm pointing out that that's not
the obviously necessarily definition. There's other definitions of virgin, which have to
do with the hymen being present or being ruptured, and here it's
defining it as not having had sex. Okay, so that's one definition,
one idea of virgin is a woman who's a virgin.
Then we go on. So and with the appropriate נפקא מינהס. nafka
minas. בתולת קרקע, Besulas karka, virgin earth, כל זמן שלא נעבדה, kol
zman shelo ne'evda, earth that's never been worked, that's never been plowed.
נפקא
מינה Nafka mina לנחל איתן, lenachal eisan, now what הלכה halacha does
it matter whether you call something virgin earth or not? Well, one
relevant is that when you do the עגלה ערופה, egla arufa, you
know when you don't know who there's... murder victim you don't know
who the murderer is, you take out this calf, you break its
neck, etc. It says you bring it into a ואדי אשר לא
עובד בו, vadi asher lo uvad bo, which has never been worked.
The ground has never been worked. So that's virgin earth. So that's
one one way in which it's relevant. Now of course it's a
little funny because the Torah doesn't call it virgin earth, the Torah
says explicitly אשר לא עובד בו,
asher
lo
uvad bo, right, that has never been that has never been worked.
So you don't really need to define what virgin earth means, I
mean the definition, the requirement for the עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa is
explicit in the Torah, or you know ground that has never been
worked. But nevertheless we're saying if it's called you know that at
least it's a concept that has relevance in הלכה, Halacha, that something
is virgin earth, it means it can be used for the עגלה
ערופה. Egla Arufa. Also נפקא מינה Nafkamina אינמי Inami למקח וממכר. lemikach
umimkar. A נפקא מינה Nafkamina is for business transactions. If basically I
have sold you ground and I've described it as virgin earth and
it turns out that it's not virgin earth then you can you
know negate the sale because it's not as I've promised it. I
for some reason I'm remembering a story about a number of years
back that a guy bought a Mercedes and you know it's supposed
to come with like leather seats and he realized that the seats
actually were the the material was this like you know fake leather,
which sometimes you get in Porsches, it really looks like leather but
it's it's fake leather. Anyway so he said something to the dealer
so the dealer like laughed at him anyway it turned into like
this major class action suit that they sued Mercedes for like millions
of dollars because they were saying it was leather, it was fake
leather. So anyway if you say it's virgin earth and it's not
virgin earth so there is relevance in הלכה Halacha for that. It's
gotta be as promised. Okay so anyway
so it says like this. Now
בתולת שקמה, besulas shikma, a virgin sycamore, what is the relevance of
this? This is a type of a tree כל זמן שלא נקטצה.
kol zman shelo niktatza. This would be a tree that you would
cut it and then it would grow back you know sort of
thicker and harder and so that would be part of the way
in which it would produce more is by sort of regular cutting.
But if you're if you're buying it you know you want one
that's that's virgin because obviously yes you'll have to cut it but
that means that you'll get more years out of it, more you
know more life out of it, it's younger. So נפקא מינה למקח
וממכר, Nafkamina lemikach umimkar, so there the relevance is for again business.
If it's promised to be virgin it has to be that it
was never cut. Anyway אינמי למקטצה בשביעית, Inami lemiktatza beshvi'is, or here's
a here's a the
there's a relevance about whether you're allowed to cut it on
שביעית, shvi'is, כדתנן תנא משנה kedisnan tana mishna אין קוצצין בתולת שקמה
בשביעית מפני שהיא עבודה, ein kotzetzin besulas shikma beshvi'is mipnei she'hi avoda,
that you cannot cut this virgin sycamore on שביעית shvi'is because that's
the way you work it is that you get it to grow
more, but if it's not virgin, if it's been cut before, then
it's not as problematic because there are some types of things you
can do on שמיטה Shmita to prevent loss which are not considered
actually working the thing itself. Anyway so here we have an interesting
ברייתא Braisa and it says there are three things that are called
virgin and what about our משנה? Mishna? Our משנה Mishna says a
woman that has never menstruated is called a בתולה, besula, בתולת דמים,
besulas damim, virgin of blood, never having had blood, with the relevance
that she doesn't have to be concerned that it happened earlier. So
how does our משנה Mishna say that and this ברייתא Braisa says
there's only three things that are called בתולה? besula?
So wait what's the problem?
This ברייתא Braisa says there are three things that are called בתולה
besula and our משנה Mishna has introduced a fourth category of בתולה,
besula, בתולת דמים, besulas damim, of
somebody a woman should be called a בתולה besula if she's never
had if she's never had her period.
Well you mean okay fine but why the category of בתולה besula
by humans when it's for נדה Nidda purposes the other is...
okay? So why does it say there are only three? There are
four types of בתולה. besula. Say there are two by humans. I
mean I know you're not impressed by the question let's see what
the גמרא Gemara has to answer. ואי איתא, ve'i isa, if it's
true that there's other category of בתולה, besula, ליתני נמי האי, lisnei
nami hai, why not mention the בתולת דמים? besulas damim? So אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak כי קתני מידי
דלית ליה שם לוואי. ki kasani midi deleis lei shem levai. When
we said there are three things that are called virgin that's without
any qualifying word. אבל מידי דאית ליה שם לוואי, aval midi de'is
lei shem levai, something that has a qualifying word לא קתני, lo
kasani, you didn't say. So if you say a woman is a
בתולה besula that means one thing, it means she's a virgin she's
never had sex. If you want to say the meaning of our
משנה Mishna that she's never had her period you would say בתולת
דמים, besulas damim, okay, virgin of blood. So therefore yes there are
three things that are called virgin without a qualifier. There's other things
that if you specify and qualify you could also use the term
virgin but it's not without a qualifier. All right fine. Now some
other answers. רב ששת בריה דרב אידי אמר Rav Sheshes brei deRav
Idi amar כי קתני מידי דתלי במעשה, ki kasani midi desali bema'aseh,
מידי דלא תלי במעשה לא קתני. midi dlo sali bema'aseh lo kasani.
No when we're saying virgin is when we said there are three
things called virgin it means that that state of virginity can be
is negated through an action, through sex, through working the earth, through
cutting the tree. Okay that's the type of virgin we're referring to
there. The virgin of blood is something that happens naturally, that that
stops being true when the woman just naturally gets her period. So
that's a different type of בתולה besula that's not the same genre
of what we were talking about.
You have all these things like מוכה עץ muka etz or what's
that?
Yeah but still... It still required some physical action to take place,
like you know, whether it be by a person. You're right. Anyway,
that gets to the question of whether
it be מוכת עץ.
mukat etz. I understand. That says, is בתולה besulah there meaning not
having the hymen or meaning having had sex? So I said I
was not going to get into that, but that we at least
it was described in the ברייתא Baraisa as not having had sex.
That is a question in הלכה, Halacha, when do we look at
the hymen, presence of the hymen, when do we look at the
question of sex? Okay, anyway, the גמרא Gemara says another answer. רב
חנינא בריה דרב איקא אמר כי קתני מידי דלא הדר לבריותו. Rav
Chanina breih deRav Ika amar ki kasani midi dela hadar livriyuso. Ah,
when did we say a virgin, that was something that if it
stops being a virgin doesn't go back to ever being a virgin.
Okay, so that's usually the case.
מידי דהדר לבריותו, Midi dehadar livriyuso, something that can go back, לא
קתני, lo kasani, we didn't say. And a woman can go back
to a state of not having her period when she becomes postmenopausal.
So,
so therefore that's not of the same category. It just I don't
know, reminds me I was I meant to look it up after
יום טוב Yom Tov but I forgot when I was looking at
this that I think Barbara Tuchman in her book on World War
II, what was her book on World War II? I forget. Anyway,
she has a good line about
Stilwell and the American experience in China.
Oh, was that it? No, maybe it was her book on World
War I. I'm trying to remember. Anyway, there was some book of
that I remember, The Guns of August. Anyway, there was some line
about how
Switzerland, I think it was Switzerland allowed certain troops to pass through
and like said something claimed like they still were going to maintain
their neutrality or something, and she had some line like, yeah, that's
about as good as like you know as as trying to restore
your virginity after you've lost it. So how you maintain your neutrality
after you've sort of acquiesced. So anyway, okay, so virgin means something
that's lost can't be restored and that's not the case of בתולת
דמים besulas damim which at some level you can get back to
not having her period.
Did I offend you there, Rachel?
Okay, alright.
Glory to you anyway.
Well, maybe my metaphor, I don't know. Anyway, okay,
where are we? Okay. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says, כי
קתני מידי דקפיד עלה זבינא. ki kasani midi dekafid alei zvina. When
are we what what are we talking about, this here's where you
get offended, what are we talking about virgin, something that people care
about. So people care about whether, you know, if they're buying land
if it's virgin earth, if they're buying a tree is it this
virgin thing, if they're marrying a woman is she a virgin? That's
something people care about. מידי דלא קפיד עלה זבינא, Midi dela kafid
alei zvina, people something people don't care about, whether a woman's had
her period or not if they're getting married, לא קתני, lo kasani,
that we didn't bother, that's not in the list. So the גמרא
Gemara said, ולא קפיד? velo kafid? Are you telling me people don't
care about that? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, רבי
חייא אומר, Rabbi Chiya omer, כשם שהשאור יפה לעיסה, keshem shehasior yafeh
la'isah, the same way yeast is good for dough, כך דמים יפים
לאשה, kach damim yafim la'ishah,
so having a lot of menstrual blood is good for a woman.
The גמרא Gemara understood that a lot of menstrual blood indicated a
healthier child.
ותני משום רבי מאיר, Vesani mishum Rabbi Meir, we taught in a
ברייתא Baraisa in the name of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, כל אשה
שדמיה מרובין, kol ishah shedameha merubin,
any woman that has a lot of blood at menstruation, בניה מרובין,
baneha merubin, will have a lot of children. It's too bad we
don't have well, you're a doctor but I Sally you probably know
this better. I because obviously a lot of menstrual blood I assume
means that there's a thicker lining. I don't know, is there any
correlation between the amount of menstrual bleeding and the fertility?
Anybody know? Out of my area of expertise. Another doctor, Sally would
know that. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara certainly thought that there was. The
גמרא Gemara I should say also another גמרא Gemara understands that the,
you know, that the man and the woman put in the ingredients
of the child and the man, the semen is like a white
matter, so that creates the white of the infant, the skin, the
teeth, and so on, and the woman who bleeds, like they didn't
know about the egg which is microscopic, that's the red matter, you
know, which is like the blood of the child and so on.
So you can understand that they thought a lot of blood meant
more children or healthier children. So if you know this medical fact,
you know, this גמרא's Gemara medical fact, then obviously you would care,
a man would care if the woman he's married has a you
know has a lot of menstrual blood when she bleeds or not
because that would impact the kids. So the idea here, now of
course the thing is that why would but yes, that might be
an issue about whether the quantity, but the issue here is whether
she's begun to have her period or not. But presumably the גמרא
Gemara understands that if she's a בתולת דמים besulas damim she has
yet to have her period, that might mean that she's you know
she doesn't have so much blood, which is obviously you know that's
not the same. One is when do you start, the other is
how much. But anyway the גמרא Gemara says so this would be
something people would be concerned about, you know, men would be concerned
about whether the woman is a בתולת דמים besulas damim or not.
So the גמרא Gemara says alright fine, אלא כי קתני מידי דקפיד
ותלי בזבינא. ela ki kasani midi dekafid vesalyi bizvina. We're talking about
when we speak about the title of virgin, not because people care
about but people want it. So people men want to marry a
woman who's a virgin, people want to buy virgin earth. everything they
want. Okay, but this מידי דלא קפיד עליה זבינא לא *midi delo
kapid alei zvina lo*. Wait, did I skip why? קפיד עליה זבינא
*kapid alei zvina*. מידי דלא קפיד עליה זבינא לא תני *midi delo
kapid alei zvina lo tanni*. But this we just said that something
people, men are not looking for. They don't want a woman who
has not yet bled. They want a woman who has because that
would indicate, A, it would certainly indicate that now she's able to
have children, which is not the point the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
making, but B, somehow the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that that correlates
also to the amount of bleeding and therefore it affects her children.
So yes, it's virgin, but not a virgin that is desirable.
I'm also confused, she'd be a child otherwise.
Yes, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, thank you for mentioning that. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* does not mention that, but yes, that is absolutely correct.
Yes.
Although one, so we say the טבע *teva* has changed. One thing
that actually has changed over the last 150-200 years is the age
of menarche. 150 years ago in most of Europe the typical age
of menarche was 17. Wow. Yeah, in France it was 15 because
it was a more prosperous country.
It has to do with health and whatever,
probably better nutrition, better health.
Now what did you just say, how long ago?
About 150 years.
But it's so funny because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that it
comes right at the age of puberty. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes
that הגיע זמנה לראות *higgia zmannah l'raot* is right at the age
of puberty, meaning 12.
Right. Rome and Persia were probably more prosperous in ancient times than
western and northern Europe were 150 years ago. Wow, fascinating. People don't
realize how... fascinating. Okay, thank you.
תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan: *Tanu Rabbanan*. איזו היא... So actually the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is our same reality. We've just leapfrogged over about a
thousand years when it wasn't the reality. Interesting, yeah, okay. That's true.
תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*. איזו היא בתולת קרקע *Eizu hi betulat karka*?
What's called בתולת קרקע *betulat karka*, virgin earth? כל שמעלה רגבים ואין
אפרקיסות *kol she'maalah regavim ve'ein afarkisot*. Anything that when you dig it
you get clumps of earth and you don't
get soft loose dirt when you dig. If you dig something you
get loose dirt, it's not virgin earth. If you dig it and
you get large clumps, then it's virgin earth. נמצא בה חרס *nimtza
bah cheres*. If you find in the earth you're digging some pieces
of pottery, little pottery shards. בידוע שנעבדה *beyadua she'ne'evda*. Then you know
that somebody's worked this earth before because how else did the pottery
shards get into the ground? So what? They get they're deep into
the earth. You mean maybe... well, that's also an interesting question, that
there is time that the level of the ground raises over hundreds
of years. So yeah, I mean yeah it's true, right now you
can dig in when they archeologically and you find pottery and so
on.
But is there a square millimeter of land in Israel where you
don't find...
Yeah, I know. Anyway. סונמא *Sunma*. If it's rock, הרי זה בתולת
קרקע *harei zeh betulat karka*. That's still considered to be virgin. You
promised somebody virgin earth and there's an area that's rock, well okay,
it still hasn't been dug. Now of course what happens if you
promise somebody land and you give them something which is all rock?
That's a different question. But as far as whether it's considered how
much can be rock or whatever, but it's still at least considered
virgin. Okay, so that was an interesting little digression about the woman
who has not bled, she's called בתולת דמים *betulat damim* and talking
about other categories of virgin. Now we go on. מעוברת משיודע עוברה
*me'uberet misheyivada ubarah*. So these again are the four women who are
considered to not be in a state of having their periods, so
if they bleed then they're not concerned 24 hours back because we
assume it just happened now, she's not in the process of bleeding
normally, so that's the הלכה halacha *halacha* of דיה שעתה dayah sha'atah
*dayyah sha'atah*. So one is a woman who's never had her period
and now we move on to the pregnant
woman. וכמה הכרת עובר *vekhamma hakarat ubar*? How much is that? What
is that stage where we say it's considered to be the pregnancy
is known? סומכוס אמר משום רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir שלשה חדשים *Sumkhos
amar mishum Rabbi Meir shelosha chadashim*, three months into the pregnancy. ואף
על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר *ve'af al pi she'ein rayah
la'davar zecher la'davar*. Although there's no proof, there's a hint to it
from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. שנאמר shenemar, *Shene'emar*. It says by תמר
*Tamar*, ויהי כמשלש חדשים *vayehi k'mishlosh chadashim*, that she after three months
it was known that she was pregnant and they were going to
burn her. So you see that three months is considered a state
to be aware that a woman is pregnant. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, זכר לדבר *zecher la'davar*? What do you mean it's only
a hint? קרא כתיב ראיה גדולה היא *kra ktiv rayah gedola hi*.
It's an explicit פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, it's a great proof. Why do
you only call it a hint? לא משום דאיכא דילדה לתשעה ואיכא
דילדה לשבעה *lo mishum deika d'yalda l'tishah ve'ika d'yalda l'shiva*. Some women
give birth at nine, after nine months, some give birth after seven
months. So the question is if a woman's giving birth after seven
months, maybe for her הכרת עוברה *hakarat ubarah* would be two and
a third months? Would be a third of the way into the
pregnancy. Maybe it wouldn't be a flat three months for all women.
So although you can't exactly prove it from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
that's what we say. Although she had twins.
That's also a different point. Okay, תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*. We're going
to talk about signs and הלכה halakha *halacha* in a minute because
let's read a little bit more.
So three months is the absolute limit, meaning...
Yeah, I'll talk about them in a minute. הרי שהייתה בחזקת מעוברת
*harei shehayeta b'chezkat me'uberet*. Let's say a woman was assumed to be
pregnant. וראתה דם *ve'ra'ata dam*. And then she bled. So we say
when she bleeds she's not worried 24 hours back because we assume
it just happened now, she's not in the process of bleeding normally,
so that's the הלכה halakha *halacha* of דיה שעתה dayah sha'atah *dayyah
sha'atah*. ואחר כך הפילה רוח ruach *ve'achar kach hipilla ruach*. Then she
never, it was not a successful pregnancy. She gave birth and it
was רוח *ruach*, like literally wind, it was not actually a viable
child or wasn't even a child at all, there was some type
of a false pregnancy. או כל דבר שאינו של קיימא o kol
davar she'eino shel kayama. or some type of a fetus that was
not viable, הרי היא בחזקתה, harei hi bechezka'tah, she's still considered to
have her status. Now the question is, going back, you know, when
she actually bled like two weeks before she had her miscarriage, does
she have to concern herself that she bled twenty-four hours back from
that day retroactively? Because now she sees it's not a successful pregnancy
that she was having, so does that mean that the bleeding is
considered to be, you know, דיה שעתה daya shaatah, or not? So
it says yes, she still has her status from before, when she
bled before, not now anymore but from before, ודיה שעתה. v'dayah sha'atah.
אף על גב שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר, af al gav she'ein
re'ayah ladavar zecher ladavar, although there's no proof there's a hint, שנאמר,
the פסוק pasuk. says, הרי חלנו כמו ילדנו, harei chalanu k'mo yaladnu,
we have been ill, it's like we have given birth, ילדנו רוח,
yaladnu ruach, like we've given birth to wind, to naught. So you
see that it uses the phrase birth for even when it's a
non-successful birth. So although it led to this woman ultimately was not—did
not carry to term, it's still considered her status is still the
same when she was pregnant. מאי זכר לדבר, mai zecher ladavar, why
are you only calling it a hint? הרי ראיה גמורה היא, harei
re'ayah g'murah hi, it's a very good proof. No, כי כתיב האי
קרא בזכרים כתיב. ki ktiv hai kra bizcharim ktiv. That verse is
only a metaphor. That verse is said about a couple of males,
not literally talking about women getting pregnant. Talking about men that as
if we were pregnant and gave birth, so it's using the words
metaphorically, it's not really directly relevant. Okay, רמיניהי, reminihi, I'll ask you
on this. קשתה שנים ולשלישי הפילה—it kashta shanayim v'lashlishi hipila says רוח
או כל דבר שאינו של קיימא. o kol davar she'eino shel kayama,
So if you remember yesterday we talked, two days ago about this
category, about a woman who gives birth and she's bleeding the few
days leading up to the childbirth. And if she bleeds and there's
never a twenty-four hour period where she had—where she's not having birth
pangs, where then it's considered that the childbirth—the child is what's bringing
about the bleeding and it does not make her a זבה. zavah.
Okay, that's the
הלכה halakha about יולדת בזוב, yoledes b'zav, is she giving childbirth as
a זבה, zavah, not if the bleeding happened with sort of pains,
birth pains, and there was no period of letting up. Now, what
happens if all of this was true, she had birth pangs, she
was bleeding, and then it was a non-successful birth? Is she considered
to have been a זבה zavah or not? The fact that it
ended in a non-successful birth, did that mean that the bleeding is
attributed to the child or not? So that's the question. קשתה שנים,
kashta shanayim, she had you know difficulty, meaning she was in pain
and she was bleeding for two days, ולשלישי הפילה רוח. v'lashlishi hipila
ruach. And on the third day she also bled, so there was
no period of letting up, but it was not a successful birth.
So או כל דבר שאינו של קיימא, she gave—or she gave birth
to something that was not viable. הרי זו יולדת בזוב, harei zo
yoledes b'zav, she is a זבה. zavah. Although she bled and although
it was with birth pangs, because it did not end in a
successful birth, we cannot attribute the bleeding to the child, to the
fetus, and therefore she's a זבה. zavah. So you see, what's the
relevance of this? You see that when it ends in a non-successful
birth, it—she doesn't have the status of being you know pregnant and
it doesn't have the halachic implications. So therefore maybe by analogy the
same should be true about the question of bleeding. So ואי אמרת
לידה מעליא היא, v'i amart leida ma'alya hi, if you say that
in the end when you give birth even if it's not viable
it's still considered to be a real birth, כל שסמוך ללידה רחמנא
טהרה, kol she'samuch l'leida rachmana tahara, so then we should say that
this bleeding is—does not make her a זבה. zavah. So you see
from the fact that the bleeding does make her a זבה zavah
when it's not successful, that if it ends to be not successful
we don't consider that status of pregnancy to have been halachically meaningful.
So why do we consider it meaningful for the question of whether
the bleeding is דיה שעתה or not? So
אמר רב פפי, amar Rav Papi, כ"ט ע"ב, kaf tes amud beis,
הני מילי מדרבנן. hanei milei miderabanan. That's a line the גמרא Gemara
likes to repeat. Don't give us a hard time, this is only
the twenty-four hour thing, it's only rabbinic, we're lenient about this. Okay,
which again תוספות Tosafot says means a lot of things are rabbinic,
but תוספות Tosafot says means this is a type of טומאה tumah
you cannot protect yourself against. You cannot be careful about. Like you
can't do anything to say I'm going to be concerned about this
and safe because it's only a טומאה tumah that applies after the
fact. The woman bleeds and then after then she's worried about the
last twenty-four hours. There's no way you can prevent it. So therefore
we're going to be more lenient. הני מילי, hanei milei, you know
what you're right, really once it was a miscarriage we should not
have considered her pregnant and we should be concerned twenty-four hours backwards,
but we're not going to be so strict about this category, we're
going to find cases, you know we're going to try to be
lenient because anyway it's something that was only applied retroactively. That's one
answer. ורב פפא אמר, v'Rav Papa amar, why retroactive?
Well,
that's basically what he's saying is that since even when we do
apply it we only apply it retroactively, like for a normal woman
who's not pregnant when she bleeds, we say everything she touched in
the last twenty-four hours, she might have already been bleeding and not
been aware and she's טמאה, temeiah, except for these categories of women
like pregnant and never had a period that we're not concerned about
that. So the whole category is making טמא tamei things
twenty-four hours after. there's
like a double retroactive. Like now we found out later it was
not successful, now retroactively we're going to make her טמאה, tamei, you
know, retroactive again 24 hours before that case. Is that clear? We
would not do that. Because the whole thing is so strict to
apply something retroactively that we're going to look for cases that we
can be lenient.
If we found out that the pregnancy wasn't viable, we just wouldn't
add that extra 24 hours.
Right, right. Sure, I mean she's טמאה tamei also when she bleeds
she's טמאה. tamei. The whole question here is about the 24 hours
prior to having bled.
Okay, but I mean after she bleeds after the pregnancy. Right. Bleeding
means she's טמאה. tamei.
Right, except I mean there's a period right after the childbirth where
a week or two weeks where the blood does not mean that,
but generally yes, that's correct. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this,
now רב פפא Rav Papa gives a better answer. It says you
can't compare the cases. רב פפא אמר, Rav Papa amar, מדי הוא
טעמא, mi di hu taama, the reason a woman when she bleeds
and she's pregnant is not is considered to be מסולקת דמים mesuleket
damim and it's דיה שעתה, right, it's considered to normally not be
in the process of getting her period, אלא משום דראשא כבד עליה
ואיברים כבדים עליה. ella mishum de-rosha kaved aleiha ve-eivarim kvedim aleiha. So
they didn't understand the whole sort of hormones relationship to the to
the bleeding, but they said why do preg- they certainly observed that
pregnant women don't bleed. Why is that? So they said well, you
know, women feel sicker when they're pregnant. Their head feels heavy, their
body feels heavy, and those things impact whether they're going to be
bleeding. That's the connection the גמרא Gemara made, that was what was
observable. Right, certain ways in which women feel when they're pregnant and
the fact they're not bleeding. So they said that reality, that's what
causes pregnant women not to bleed. That reality doesn't change whether the
pregnancy ends successfully or not. That reality remains true regardless of how
the pregnancy ends. We could say the hormonal reality remains the same
regardless of whether it ends successfully. רב פפא Rav Papa says don't
compare. One question is was the bleeding as a result of the
child. So that we could say it's only defined to be connected
to the child if it was a viable child. That's a הלכה
halakha definition that we say the child caused the bleeding and that's,
you know, that's only if the child is viable. But here we're
saying is this pregnant woman, can she expect to get to be
bleeding or not expect to get her period? And the answer is
no, doesn't matter whether it's going to end successfully or not. A
pregnant woman should not be expected to get her period and that's
what's relevant.
Is there a נפקא מינה? nafka mina? What? Is there a נפקא
מינה nafka mina that it's attributed to the child?
Attributed to the child is about if she bleeds right before the
pregnancy she is זבה zavah as well.
Right, she bleeds three days and then she gives birth, does that
mean if you attribute it to the child then then she's not
a זבה. zavah. If you don't attribute it to the child then
she's a זבה, zavah, okay, if she's bleeding during that period.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי ראשא ואיברים כבדים עליה. hacha
nami rosha ve-eivarim kvedim aleiha. Here too even if it did not
succeed, that's the reality is pregnant women don't bleed and therefore it
doesn't matter if it ends successfully or not. Now, בעי מיני רב
ירמיה מרב זירא. baei minei Rav Yirmiyah me-Rav Zeira. רב ירמיה Rav
Yirmiyah asked רב זירא: Rav Zeira: ראתה דאחר הוכר עוברה מהו? rashah
de-achar hukkara u-bara mahu?
Let's say she bled and then you started seeing that she was
pregnant a week later, her it was obvious. So obviously she was
pregnant a week before, it just wasn't visible yet. So do we
say that the fact that she bled even though and we know
she was pregnant but it was at an earlier stage, right what
is her status being pregnant at an earlier stage, does that also
make her מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim or not? Bleeding at an early
stage. Bleeding, bleeding while she's pregnant but prior to three months. Right.
Does is that is that state of being pregnant but prior to
three months considered to be מסולקת דמים? mesuleket damim? Now here's the
science and הלכה halakha question. Because if you would ask us you
would say the answer is obviously yes, once a woman is pregnant,
straight through, you know, there's no not going to now of course,
again I really wish Sally was here today because I think for
some women at early stages of pregnancy there still is some breakthrough
bleeding. I but I'm not sure if it's connected to early stages
or just could be at any period. Do you know? Any of
the doctors in the room know?
Not connected to her period. Not a good sign.
Aha. Some women do have breakthrough bleeding during pregnancy, either particularly at
the beginning, the end, or just random.
It's random, but it has nothing to do with her period.
Okay, right. That I know. Right. With yeah. So right.
Although for
הלכות נדה hilkhot niddah whether it's really bleeding of menstrual bleeding or
just any bleeding, not there's not much of a הלכה halakha difference,
it's more about the time rather than about the biological reality. But
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara asks what about bleeding during the three
months the first three months before the the three month line? Is
that is she considered מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim during that period? Now
we would say yes, right? It's the same reality of being pregnant,
doesn't matter it's earlier than that. And by the way there's an
important נפקא מינה nafka mina and this gets again to the science
and הלכה halakha question. Let's say you can determine pregnancy less than
three months like nowadays you can do a pregnancy test. Would that
have the same הלכה halakha or not, or do you need the
three months? So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer to this
is. שמע. shema. So do we say like this? כיון דבעידנא דחזיא
לא הוכר עוברה מטמיא. keivan de-be-idna de-hazaya lo hukkara u-bara mitamya.
Do we say since at the moment she saw the fetus was
not yet visible, so therefore she is טמאה tamei twenty-four hours back,
it does not yet have that status? או דלמא O dilma or
do we say כיון דסמוך לחזאי keivan desamuch lachazai since you saw
right before it became visible, לא מטמיא lo mitamya she doesn't it
doesn't tamei twenty-four hours back, since it was visible very soon after,
obviously she was already in that state. And obviously the Gemara knew
she was pregnant, but it's clear from the Gemara's question, Tosafot emphasizes
that it was near that state, that the Gemara assumes that only
when this pregnancy gets to the stage of three months or near
that period, does it have the effect. And let's look at the
Gemara's answer. אמר ליה Amar lei says it back, מידי הוי טעמא
midei havei taama what's the reason she's considered to be not not
expecting her period, not bleeding, מסולקת דמים? mesuleket damim? אלא משום דראשיה
כביד עליה ואיבריה כבידין עליה ella mishum deroshya kavid alei veeivarya kveidin
alei because her head feels heavy, her body feels heavy. So בעידנא
דחזאי beidana dechazai when she sees before three months, אין ראשיה כביד
עליה ואין איבריה כבידין עליה ein roshya kavid alei veein eivarya kveidin
alei that reality doesn't set in yet, right? Women don't start feeling
nauseous and other things, I guess as a general rule till they're
a little bit into their pregnancy. True?
Yes. Okay. Anyway, till they're in their second trimester. So therefore in
their first trimester you don't have that physiological reality.
No, first trimester is when it's the worst.
Is that about nausea? How about just feeling heavy, like what the
Gemara describes?
You feel so heavy when you're ripe, but before you feel sick,
most people get their sickness then. Uh-huh.
And how about the phenomenon the Gemara is describing which is like
a feeling heavy head, heavy limbs, like weighed down? That's at the
end when the actual fetus feels heavy. And right okay and you're
carrying the extra weight.
Really? Okay anyway but this is what the Gemara says, it connects
the fact of no blood to this feeling, this very heavy feeling.
Right. Exactly. And therefore and therefore according to the Gemara it only
kicks in this state only kicks in at the three-month period even
if they were obviously they were pregnant before, and which leads to
interesting questions. Nowadays that we understand that the correlation is based on
the hormones and that it begins immediately, will that change this status
to be able to begin as soon as a woman is known
to be pregnant? Now you'll say who cares? We don't have this
whole twenty-four-hour retroactive thing anyway. Well we're about to find out who
cares because now the Gemara actually turns it into a practical issue
for us even today. So let's take a look. בעי מיניה ההוא
סבא
מרבי יוחנן, Bei minei hahu saba meRabbi Yochanan, so a certain elder
asked Rabbi Yochanan the following question. הגיע וסתה בימי עיבורה, Higeia vestah
bimei iburah,
the time she's expected to get her period happened during her pregnancy.
Okay let's say a woman generally expects to get her period every
thirty days and now she's pregnant and it was thirty days from
the last time she had her period before actually that would be
let's see. A woman had her period then would get pregnant fifteen
days later, so she'd only be two weeks pregnant.
She'd only be
two weeks pregnant and according to the Gemara you wouldn't know that.
But the Gemara also understands that there are examples of וסת vesset
which are not based on spaces but based on for example what
day of the month. So the Gemara understands that there could be
a וסת vesset like a woman who sees every ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh. So let's say she's might be she's two months pregnant or
whatever but it's still a ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh now, into three
months into the pregnancy it's still a little hard to understand how
this exactly happens because if she has to be three months pregnant
then it's been three months since she's had her last period and
then that undermines her וסת, vesset, right? Because once three periods pass
where you don't get your previous period, that undermines your previous וסת.
vesset.
Or at least two periods have passed.
How would that happen if it was every ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
and three oh I guess you could do it if you got
if you got pregnant on the second of a month?
No.
You're bleeding on the third month you're three months pregnant counting from
your last period.
Yeah you went over three
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh so you always have two months that didn't
you didn't erase the וסת. vesset.
Does that work? Okay I have to figure it out. Anyway you
have to imagine maybe it's a woman that has her period every
other ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, who knows? But this is his question.
The time for her period has come and she's pregnant. Does she
have to worry about her period now? Because the הלכה halacha? is
and this is a very relevant הלכה halacha nowadays for הלכות נדה
hilkhot niddah that the day a woman is expected her period the
couple can't have sex or the time the half-day the if it's
day-time or night-time because obviously that would be irresponsible. Might be a
פסוק pasuk, וזהרתם את בני ישראל מטמאתם vehizartem et bnei Yisrael mitumatam
that you have to separate when you're expecting to get your period
because you don't want to be having sex and then the woman
gets her period and then you're winding having sex when she's in
when the woman is a נדה. niddah. So let's say you but
the הלכה halakha. is or question is do you have to worry
about it if you're in the category of מסולקת דמים? mesuleket damim?
So a woman is pregnant, can the couple have sex even on
the day she normally would expect to get her period because the
fact that she's pregnant will tell her that she's not going to
get her period even though it's the normal day she would have
expected otherwise.
So that's the question we're seeing but don't we usually assume that
we had a חזקה chazaka already which was three months and then
what would be the problem?
No well that's why I was that's what I was trying to
figure out how do you get to be three months pregnant. and
still have the day of your period?
Is it even so possible then?
Right, let's imagine. Well, for us, it's very possible with which is
what I'm going to get to, which is let's say the woman
has taken a pregnancy test. Do you have to now worry about
the period? That's why the question about this being relevant today and
how much you still go by the three months. But let's imagine
in the גמרא Gemara that it was a period every other month.
Okay, so now she's three months into her pregnancy, should she be
worried about her period? So let's take a look. הגיע
עת וסתה בימי עבורה, Higi'a et vestah bimei iburah, so that time
has come during her pregnancy, ולא בדקה, v'lo badkah, she didn't check
herself after that day that she was expecting passed to see whether
she had her period or not. מהו, Mahu, what's the הלכה? קמיבעיא
ליה אליבא דמאן דאמר וסתות דאורייתא. Ka mibaya lei aliba d'man d'amar
vestot d'oraita. My question is according to the one that says that
וסתות, vestot, that you expect the נדה nidah that you have to
anticipate your period on that day is a biblical concern and that
biblically you have to anticipate that you're going to get it and
that even more than that, even after that day passed, if you
haven't checked, you have to assume biblically that it has happened unless
you can counter-prove it. Okay, so that if that was the day
you were expecting, you have to assume it happened unless you can
prove otherwise. So מאי, mai, what do we say? כיון דוסתות דאורייתא,
Keivan d'vestot d'oraita, if it's biblical, do we say בעיא בדיקה, ba'ei
bdikah, we need to check, או דילמא, od dilma, and even though
she's in this category of being pregnant, או דילמא, od dilma, or
do we say, כיון דדמיה מסולקין, keivan d'dama mesulakim, since she's pregnant
and her blood is considered to be removed, לא בעיא בדיקה, lo
ba'ei bdikah, she doesn't need to check, that's a good enough proof
that it didn't happen. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to
him, מיתיבי, meituva, I can prove it to you from a משנה.
Mishna. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, Rabbi Meir says, כל אם
היתה במחבא והגיע שעת וסתה, kol im hayeta b'machava v'higi'a sh'at vestah,
if a woman was in a cave, she was hiding, you know,
because of the Romans or whatever, that's the assumed scenario or something
like that, and then her time of her period came, ולא בדקה,
v'lo badkah, she didn't check, טהורה, tehorah, she can still assume she's
טהורה. tehorah. Why even though it's the time of her period? שהחרדה
מסלקת את הדמים. Shecharadah mesaleket et hadamim.
Fear causes the blood to be withheld. True? Yes? No? No? Stress?
What about stress?
No, you can't get your period when you're stressed.
That's because of malnutrition, starvation, that wasn't because
of trauma.
Okay. All right.
She's the one who would know.
We'll have to ask the expert. All right, moving on. So anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says, טעמא דאיכא חרדה, ta'ama d'ika charadah, so
you see the reason you don't have to be concerned and you
can assume טהור tahor is because of the fear. הא ליכא חרדה,
Ha leka charadah, if there was no fear, והגיע וסתה ולא בדקה,
v'higi'a vestah v'lo badkah, and the time came without checking, טמאה. tmeiah.
The implication is is that were it not for this special case,
she'd have to assume she's טמאה tmeiah after this time has passed.
What's the bigger issue? What is the concern?
The concern is that you
don't really know that you're pregnant? Is it or no, no, no.
You mean why is the גמרא Gemara. concerned about bleeding?
No, I mean this is a funny thing. They're saying that they're,
that you're pregnant. Right. And we know that when you're pregnant, you're
not going to bleed unless of course you bleed while you're pregnant,
which can happen. Okay, right. But now we've established you're pregnant and
then
at a time where normally before you got pregnant would have your
period, why
would we be on alert?
What, why would we be concerned?
So that's a good question. Right. Well, in the end the גמרא
Gemara is going to say you don't, so you can be happy
with the conclusion. What's the question? I would say, so I would
say two possibilities. One is, which seems somewhat probably the more likely,
is the גמרא Gemara did not know the science as well as
we did, right? So the גמרא Gemara assumed the, not so much
like the reality of the hormones is that you don't get your
period when you're pregnant. If so, then you wouldn't even understand what
the question is. It assumed that it was let's not deal with
the pregnancy. Let's deal with the case of stress. Let's assume for
argument's sake that stress could impact getting, I'm not saying it does,
but let's assume the גמרא Gemara believes it does. So even though
it could impact whether you get your period, the question is yeah,
maybe, but maybe the period will come regardless of the stress. So
how good is the reality of the stress enough to say you
don't have to worry about it at all? So the גמרא Gemara
thought that pregnancy was similar. It didn't think that the reality of
pregnancy meant biologically no period. It thought that the symptoms of feeling
heavy and whatever, like stress, had an impact. So it wants to
know how certain is it that we can not be concerned at
all with the period just because you have this state of pregnancy.
So it did not know the same certainty that we do about
the correlation of pregnancy and no period.
Don't you think the women would say that they were pregnant?
I don't think so. I don't think so. I mean you could
speculate but I just think that the גמרא Gemara felt that the
period is still regular. The woman is still on the clock but
there's something interrupting it. The stress, the feeling of being heavy but
the clock is still going and there's something jamming the works. So
they just, that's it. Yes, I think that's clear. That I think
is clear. And therefore the question is how confident can we be
not to be concerned about it.
But let's say she could tell you though. But let's say she
can tell you though, but she's under a period of intense stress,
then what if you have fear?
I don't know, let's see what the answer is. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so the only reason רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says don't
worry is because of the fear, which assumes that the normal cases
without the fear, once the period has passed, you have to assume
she's טמאה tamei without checking.
אלמא וסתות דאורייתא Alma vestos d'oraisa shows that we're concerned that the
the fact that we assume a period predicts that she will bleed
is biblical, which means that her status is considered to be טמאה
tamei unless we can prove otherwise. We are so confident that the,
right, that the period that she's expecting, the time she's expecting to
get her period is so good of a predictor that we're going
to assume she's טמאה tamei after that time has passed unless we
prove otherwise. And that's encapsulated by the phrase וסתות דאורייתא, vestos d'oraisa,
a biblical concern and that's her status until we can prove otherwise.
And even so, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that the reality of
stress is enough to override that concern. So you see, וכיון דאיכא
חרדא, vekeivan d'ika charada, nevertheless, because of the fear, דמיה מסולקין, dameha
mesulakin, the blood is we assume not there and that overrides even
this predictor which is assumed to be a very strong predictor. ולא
בעי בדיקה, v'lo ba'ei bdika, she doesn't need to check. הכא נמי
דמיה מסולקין ולא בעי בדיקה. hacha nami dameha mesulakin v'lo ba'ei bdika.
The same is true about pregnancy. Even though, even though the expectation
of getting her period would normally be a biblical concern, the reality
of being pregnant is a strong enough counter-evidence or that we don't
even have to check and she can assume she doesn't get her
period. And now the question becomes nowadays a woman does a pregnancy
test, right? She right away knows she's pregnant. Does she have to,
her and her husband not have sex on the day she would
normally expect to get her period? So רב משה Rav Moshe has
like a תשובה teshuva about that, you know, about using pregnancy tests
and not having to do the three months. But realize though it's
a חידוש chiddush to say that in terms of like the whole
science and הלכה for two reasons. Number one, it's just it's one
thing to say we have better ways of detecting it than the
גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara needed to see it more visibly, we
can detect it. But remember we're also saying that our science is
better than the גמרא Gemara and we're going to פסקן pasken on
our science. Because the גמרא Gemara said it's not about whether she
was pregnant, it's about three months and feeling heavy. And we say
you go by a pregnancy test and no, it's not really about
feeling heavy in three months. It's about being pregnant and it's about
the hormones. Okay, so there's actually some discussion in the פוסקים. poskim.
If memory serves correctly, רב משה Rav Moshe says you can use
the pregnancy test and not have to... I'll double check that. Okay,
so that is the pregnant woman. Now we go on to the
nursing woman.
It says לא בדיקה lo bdika because even if you checked and
found blood it wouldn't mean anything?
No, if she checked and found, then you're טמאה. tamei. But it
means you don't need to check. You assume טהורה tehorah even without
checking. Okay. Now מניקה, menika, a nursing woman is also considered to
be מסולקת דמים mesulekes damim and if she sees she doesn't have
to be worried 24 hours back, and that's until she weans the
child. But as we saw in the משנה, Mishnah, רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir said it's the reality of weaning and the חכמים Chachamim say
it's
24 months from the time the child is born. תנו רבנן: מניקה
שמת בנה, menika shemeis b'nah, if you have a nursing woman whose
God forbid her child dies בתוך עשרים וארבעה חודש besoch esrim v'arba
chodesh within the 24 months which is normally considered to be the
standard period of nursing, הרי
היא ככל הנשים, harei hi kechol hanashim, she goes back to being
like all women, meaning she's not considered to be מסולקת דמים, mesulekes
damim, removed of blood. ומטמא מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה, umetamei me'eis le'eis
umipkida lipkida, she is טמאה tamei backwards 24 hours or till the
last time she checked. Because it goes by the reality of nursing.
ולפיכך אם היתה מניקתו והולכת ארבע וחמש שנים, ulifichach im haysa menikaso
v'holeches arba v'chamesh shanim, once it goes by the reality of nursing
and not by a time period, the same is true to be
lenient. Let's say she was nursing her child four or five years.
דייה שעתה, dayah sha'atah, she would also remain in the category of
nursing. It's about the reality. So if that reality stops early then
it stops. But if it goes on later then it goes on.
It's all about the reality of nursing. If she nursed for one
month and then stopped? If she nursed for one month and stopped,
then her status stops. So her status? Oh you mean she has
to first have one the first time of bleeding? No, it seems
like it's right away. But okay, the status of a nursing woman
is as long as she is actively nursing. That's what רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says, whether to be lenient or strict. רבי יהודה ורבי
יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rebbi Yehuda v'Rebbi Yossi v'Rebbi Shimon omrim, however
now you have three other תנאים Tanaim who disagree, who say דייה
שעתה, dayah sha'atah, no, כל עשרים וארבעה חודש, kol esrim v'arba chodesh,
it does not go by the reality of nursing, it goes by
24 months since childbirth. We assume since that's the normal period of
nursing for the first 24 months she is not normally, will not
normally bleed regardless of the reality. ולפיכך, ulifichach, now by the way
as far as what we know, again doctors correct me if I'm
wrong, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is correct here, right? It goes the
reality of nursing, right? Isn't it that the the sucking of the
child releases certain sort of what is it like you know?
You can still get pregnant.
What? You can... yeah, even that's not so not 100%, but at
least that does to some degree withhold, right,
prevent the menstruation. Anyway, okay, so they say ולפיכך אם היתה מניקתו
ארבע וחמש שנים, ulifichach im haysa menikaso arba v'chamesh shanim, once it
is about 24 months, not about the reality of nursing, so then
if she was nursing longer, מטמא מעת לעת ומפקידה לפקידה, metamei me'eis
le'eis umipkida lipkida, then it doesn't matter, once you're out of 24
months she goes back. be like a normal woman and she's טמא
tamei then 24 hours back from the time she sees. Okay, so
basically רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it always goes by the reality
of nursing whether a little or a lot, and the חכמים Chachamim
say it always goes by 24 months, regardless of whether the nursing
was a little or the nursing was a lot, it's always going
to go for by 24 months. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
כשתמצא לומר, kishetimtza lomar, when you want you could say, and this
really means we are going to say, meaning we can't prove it,
but it seems to be that what are they debating? Here's what
they're debating. לדברי רבי מאיר, Lidvrei Rabbi Meir, דם נעכר ונעשה חלב.
dam ne'ekar vena'aseh chalav. The reason רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that
she doesn't have to be concerned about getting her period while she's
nursing is because he says how does a woman make milk? How
does the body lactate? The blood that otherwise would be menstrual blood
gets transformed into milk. Okay, so talking about having a slightly different
science than ours. So therefore as long as she is nursing, as
long as her body is producing milk, she's not going to have
her menstrual period because the blood is being removed and being transformed
into milk.
And this is by people too, they have the same principle by
animals.
All right, לדברי רבי יוסי, רבי יהודה, רבי שמעון, Lidvrei Rabbi Yose,
Rabbi Yehuda, Rabbi Shimon, according to the other תנאים, Tannaim, no, it
has nothing to do with the reality of nursing. Why does she
not bleed after childbirth? Because איבריה מתפרקין ואין נפשה חוזרת עד עשרים
וארבע חודש, eivareha mitparkin v'ein nafsha chozeret ad esrim v'arba chodesh, her
body feels like disjointed and she does not get back her strength
for 24 years months after childbirth. So it's because of the weakness
of her body and that really is not about the nursing at
all, it's just about 24 months after childbirth her body still has
not recovered.
So what if she were not going into that category? Exactly.
Right, exactly. לפיכך, Lefichach, now, the גמרא Gemara says, לפיכך דרבי מאיר
למה לי? Lefichach d'Rabbi Meir lama li? Why did רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir have to spell out, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said therefore if
she nurses longer, it's going to also be have the status even
for four or five years? It's obvious, you told me it's about
the reality of nursing. So it says no, משום לפיכך דרבי יוסי,
mishum Lefichach d'Rabbi Yose, because he's responding to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
who says 24 months, so he's just sort of saying no, you
say always 24 months regardless how long, I disagree, I say however
long she's nursing. ולפיכך דרבי יוסי למה לי? Uleifichach d'Rabbi Yose lama
li? Why did רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose have to spell it out
again? רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says 24 months, so why do you
I mean, you know, we could figure that out ourselves. Why do
you have to say therefore if it's four or five years she
goes back to the other status? No, מהו דתימא רבי יוסי תרתי
אית ליה קמשמע לן, mahu d'teima Rabbi Yose tarti it leh kamashma
lan,
because maybe with you could hold either is good enough to make
her מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. Meaning, you could have held, you know,
either it's 24 months even if she stopped nursing, and if she
continued nursing it will go till four or five years. Either one
could be sufficient to cause her to be מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim.
So therefore רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose had to spell out, no, I
go just by 24 months and if it goes longer that doesn't
do anything for me, just 24 months. ורבי מאיר v'Rabbi Meir says,
and I go just by nursing, and whether it's shorter or longer
it always goes by the reality of nursing. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara continues. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly
that this is what the debate is about. דם נעכר ונעשה חלב
דברי רבי מאיר. Dam ne'ekar vena'aseh chalav divrei Rabbi Meir. So here
a ברייתא Beraita says it explicitly: the blood congeals and turns into
milk, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir? says, so as long as
the milk is coming out she's not going to bleed. רבי יוסי
אומר איבריה מתפרקין ואין נפשה חוזרת עליה עד עשרים וארבע חודש. Rabbi
Yose omer eivareha mitparkin v'ein nafsha chozeret aleiha ad esrim v'arba chodesh.
No, her body feels disjointed, she does not recover for 24 months.
אמר רבי אילעא, Amar Rabbi Ila'a, מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? mai ta'ama
d'Rabbi Meir? What's the reasoning of רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir Where does
he get this idea that how the milk gets made? דכתיב, Dechtiv,
the verse says, מי יתן טהור מטמא לא אחד? Mi yiten tahor
mitamei lo echad? Who will make, who will give something pure from
something impure? Is it not the One? Is it not God? A
verse from איוב. Iyov. Well, every פסוק pasuk from איוב Iyov is
poetry and impossible to understand, but okay. So here you have this
very obscure verse, but טהור tahor comes from טמא. tamei. So something
pure comes from something impure. What does this mean? It means milk
comes from blood, from the blood of a woman, menstrual blood, which
would normally be impure. ורבנן, Verabbanan, and what did the Rabbis say?
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו שכבת זרע שהיא טמאה ואדם
נוצר ממנה טהור. zu shichvat zera shehi tme'ah v'adam notzar mimena tahor.
Now this means what's טהור tahor that comes from טמא? tamei? This
is the semen which is also טמא tamei of a man and
that turns into a human. It's a nice interesting parallel, right? That
you know the things that create the child, the menstruation and the
semen are טמא tamei and then the thing it transforms into something
טהור. tahor. I'm sure there's a nice sermon in there somewhere. Okay,
so now רבי אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Elazar omer, so רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar has a different explanation of this פסוק. pasuk אלו מי נדה.
Elu mei niddah. Now here נדה niddah does not mean נדה niddah
as we've been talking this whole מסכת, masechet, it means what the
תורה Torah calls מי נדה, mei niddah, waters of נדה, niddah, נדה
niddah can mean sprinkling. So it's the waters of the פרה
אדומה. Parah Adumah. Okay, שהמזה מזין עליו טהור, shehamaze mazin alav tahor,
the one who sprinkles and is sprinkled upon becomes טהור, tahor, purifies
him, והנוגע, v'hanogei'a, but if you touch the waters, טמא. tamei. So
this is the classic right paradox of פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, that
if you touch the water you're טמא tamei but the sprinkler and
sprinklee become are טהור. tahor. So that is the thing that causes
two also causes purity. So now the גמרא Gemara questions this הלכה.
The גמרא Gemara says ומזה טהור? umazzeh tahor? Can you really say
the sprinkler is טהור? tahor? והכתיב vehakativ there's a פסוק, pasuk, ומזה
מי הנדה יכבס בגדיו, umazzeh mei haniddah yechabbes begadav, the one who
sprinkles it has to clean his clothes, which means that he is
טמא tamei and his clothes
are טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מאי מזה mai
mazzeh doesn't literally mean the sprinkler. It means נוגע, nogea, if you
touch it. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והכתיב מזה והכתיב
נוגע? vehakativ mazzeh vehakativ nogea? There's one verse says the sprinkler is
טמא tamei and another verse says the one who touches is טמא.
tamei. So clearly both of them are טמא. tamei. ועוד, מזה בעי
טבילה ונוגע לא בעי טבילה. ve'od, mazzeh ba'i tibbul venogea lo ba'i
tibbul. And number two, the פסוק pasuk really does mean the sprinkler
because the פסוק says when the person touches it, it says he
is טמא tamei but not his clothes. Whereas if it says if
you sprinkle it, it says you and your clothes are טמא. tamei.
So clearly they're both טמא, tamei, not only that, the המזה's hamazzeh
worse than the נוגע. nogea. So therefore, how do you say that
the sprinkler is not טמא? tamei? אלא מאי מזה, ella mai mazzeh,
okay, but you know what, מזה mazzeh of the verse does not
mean the sprinkler. What does it mean? נושא. noseh. It means if
you carry it, not if you actually sprinkle it. והגמרא Vehagemara says
וליכתב נושא? velichtav noseh?
So why doesn't it just say if you carry it you're טמא?
tamei? קמשמע לן דעד דדרי כשיעור הזאה. kamashma lan de'ad darei keshi'ur
haza'ah.
You're not טמא tamei unless you carry the amount of the water
that normally you would be the minimum amount that you need to
sprinkle on somebody. But again it's not referring to the one who
actually sprinkles, it's referring to one who carries the amount of water
that would be required for that.
Oh, that's a good question.
Okay, תוספות Tosafot says, הניחא למאן דאמר הזאה צריכה שיעור. haniha leman
de'amar haza'ah tzericha shi'ur.
So that's good if you say there's a minimum amount for sprinkling.
אלא למאן דאמר אין צריכה שיעור, ella leman de'amar ein tzericha shi'ur,
if there's not a minimum amount, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar?
What can you say? אפילו למאן דאמר אינה צריכה שיעור, afillu leman
de'amar einah tzericha shi'ur, even if there isn't a minimum amount, הני
מילי אגבא דגברא. hani milei agabba degabra. That means there's not a
minimum amount that has to hit the person you're sprinkling on, even
one drop makes him טהור. tahor. אבל במנא, aval bemana, but in
the vessel that you're dipping the hyssop into, there has to be
a minimum amount of water in that vessel. בעינא שיעור. ba'ina shi'ur.
There is a minimum amount. דתנן, כמה יהא במים ויהא בהן כדי
הזאה? detnan, kama yehei bamayim veyehei bahen kedei haza'ah? How much is
it considered that there's enough water for sprinkling? Now of course the
amount here is just practically the amount you need. כדי שיטבול ראשי
גבעולים, kedei sheyitbol roshei givolim, enough water that you can dip the
tops of the like, you know, of the hyssop, whatever those called,
the whatever buds?
What are those called? Ears I guess or whatever. ויזה, veyazah, and
sprinkle. So there has to be enough water that you can physically
get the stuff wet and successfully sprinkle on the person. Okay, anyway,
so therefore what we have said based on this read of the
פסוק, and Michael asked of course a great question, what is motivating
the גמרא Gemara to say that the פסוק is not literal? But
we'll bracket that for now. It's saying that although the Torah says
the sprinkler is טמא, tamei, we actually say the sprinkler is טהור,
tahor, only if you touch or carry it. But if you're actually
directly involved in the process of being sprinkled on or doing the
sprinkling, you are טהור. tahor. So this thing which causes טומאה tumah
to people outside of the process causes טהרה taharah to people who
are in the process. And that's טמא, tamei, טהור tahor comes from
טמא. tamei. והיינו דאמר שלמה, vehainu de'amar Shlomo, that's what שלמה Shlomo
said, אמרתי אחכמה והיא רחוקה ממני. amarti echkama vehia rechoka mimenni.
Right? The classic statement of the גמרא Gemara that פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah is the classic חוק, chok, the thing that's impossible to understand.
שלמה Shlomo said I thought I would become wise and I realized
that I cannot really understand everything because here I can't understand how
the same thing that makes some people טמא tamei makes other people
טהור. tahor. Okay, again there's a good sermon in that but we
won't elaborate on that right now. All right, so anyway that is
why רבי מאיר says it goes by the reality of nursing because
the milk according to him comes from the blood. The rabbis disagree.
Now we get to the third category of a person who is
מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. We had pre-menopause, fourth category, excuse me. Pregnant,
nursing, and now the fourth which is post-menopause. איזו היא זקנה? eizehu
hi zekeinah? What is an elder woman that is considered מסולקת דמים?
mesuleket damim? שעברו עליה שלש עונות סמוך לזקנתה. she'avru aleiha shalosh onot
samuch leziknata. For
three periods, three normal cycles have passed without bleeding, and it's at
the time when she is getting closer to her old age.
Now that begs the question.
The גמרא's Gemara going to get to. היכי דמי סמוך לזקנתה? heichi
dami samuch leziknata? How do you define close to her old age?
אמר רב יהודה, כל שחברותיה אומרות עליה זקנה היא. amar Rav Yehuda,
kol shechaveroteha omrot aleiha zekeinah hi.
Any woman that people are saying oh yeah she's old, she's an
older woman, זקנה היא. zekeinah hi. That doesn't say anybody that's a
member of the AARP or you know get discounts on their subway
tickets. Okay, anyway so somebody that's perceived as being elderly. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, כל שקורין לה
אמא אמא ואינה בושה. kol shekorein lah imma imma ve'eina bosha. Anyone
that people will call her mother, which sort of means like grandma
in this context maybe, that the double language אמא אמא imma imma
though some only have one of the אמאs. imma And she's not
embarrassed. Now of course
as תוספות Tosafot says, what does it matter if she's embarrassed, right?
How does that determine what the reality is, what her psychological response
is? So תוספות Tosafot says it's talking about that a normal woman
of that age would or would not be embarrassed, and that's a
way of measuring and determining is she of that age.
Yeah, it's such an ironic discussion or
Amoraic I believe because this
is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon usually yeah
this side has the years for ריש לקיש Resh Lakish and the
whole set. It's all Aramaic here it's clearly that era everybody here
is an אמורא. Amora. Let me let me read a little bit
more. רב זירא Rav Zeira רב שמואל בר רב יצחק Rav Shmuel
bar Rav Yitzchak חד אמר chad amar there's another debate some say
כל שאינה מקפדת kol she'eina makpedes that she doesn't mind, she doesn't
get upset. וחד אמר vechad amar כל שאינה בושה kol she'eina bousha
the other says they call her a grandma but one says כל
שאינה מקפדת kol she'eina makpedes that she doesn't mind, she doesn't get
upset. וחד אמר vechad amar כל שאינה בושה kol she'eina bousha the
other says they call her a grandma she doesn't get embarrassed. מאי
בינייהו mai beinaihu
what's a case that would be a difference between them? So you
would say if you had to ask which case could you have
that had one and not the other I would assume it would
be a woman who's, well let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer
is. איכא בינייהו ika beinaihu בושה ואינה מקפדת. bousha ve'eina makpedes. She's
embarrassed but she doesn't object. Now that's a little funny you would
assume that embarrassment comes later that you might object and then you
only get embarrassed later but anyway the גמרא Gemara assumes that you
might be embarrassed but you don't you're not you're not willing to
verbally object like מקפדת makpedes means in your mind you object, you
imagine that your mental objection comes before stage when you actually get
embarrassed. But presumably the גמרא Gemara understands מקפדת makpedes is that you
mean so you actually say something about it. You say stop calling
me that, okay? So maybe you're embarrassed but you're not yet ready
to tell people stop calling me that. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. Now again the interesting question here is you know תוספות
Tosafot takes it out of the psychological reality that it's not whether
you actually are embarrassed or upset but whether normal women would be
embarrassed or upset at this age but you still wonder that it's
something to do with perception, it doesn't give a actually fixed age.
Why wouldn't it say fifty, sixty? Why doesn't it give an age?
That's much more quantifiable. So presumably the גמרא Gemara understood that women
are different, some women could be you know at different ages some
will be postmenopausal some won't, and the גמרא also assumed and I
assume this is not correct that there's a correlation between how old
you look and when you become postmenopausal because according to the גמרא
a lot had to do with are you perceived as being old
and would you be upset that people are calling you this because
of how you are perceived. So again I assume the גמרא seems
to feel that it's a correlation not of age but of you
know how old that you look. I assume that's not correct do
we know can somebody happen to have any information here? I mean
I know there's a wide range of when women become postmenopausal and
I'm guessing but I could be wrong that it's not really correlated
to how old they look but maybe it is I don't know.
Of course not. No?
What
makes you look old is that estrogen leaves your body. Uh-huh.
So this is the same thing that happens in
menopause.
Yeah exactly.
So you say there is a correlation between how old you look
and when you become postmenopausal? I'm saying correlation not causal. No. So
wait so you're saying there is a correlation between how old you
look and whether you're postmenopausal?
Of course because it's in the opposite direction the causality.
Well it doesn't matter what way the causality is as long as
it's a correlation. Absolutely. Oh so okay so look at that so
the גמרא was absolutely right.
Then there needs to be
staying out in the sun makes you destroys your skin which
can make you look older. Okay right and health and all those
things but at least if there's some positive correlation
it's absolutely true I mean the hormones that the hormones associated with
being pre-
pre-menopausal keep you looking young.
Okay so that's great so here so so actually the science is
correct here because the גמרא does not give a strict age it
speaks about how a woman is perceived which means how old she
looks and what we're hearing is that there's a positive correlation between
between how old a woman looks and whether she's postmenopausal. Let me
read one one more sentence and we'll end with
that. Okay. וכמה עונה vekama ona we say three עונות onot have
to pass when even after she looks this way till she's considered
to be without bleeding till she's considered to be postmenopausal. How much
is that? אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי יהודה נשיאה amar Resh Lakish
mishum Rabbi Yehuda Nesia עונה בינונית שלושים יום ona beinonit shloshim yom
the average cycle which is thirty days so meaning ninety days passes.
The גמרא assumes that an average woman thirty days, ninety days passes
without bleeding and she looks older and therefore she's considered
postmenopausal. ורבא אמר רב חסדא עשרים יום v'Rava amar Rav Chisda esrim
yom and they say twenty days and the גמרא says לא פליגי
lo pligi they don't really debate מר קחשיב ימי טומאה וימי טהרה
mar kachashiv yemei tumah v'yemei tahara one is considering the whole period
of the cycle the טומאה tumah period the seven days of where
she's a נידה niddah and then and then the twenty three days
of not being a נידה niddah till she bleeds again so that's
thirty. ומר לא חשיב ימי טומאה umar lo chashiv yemei tumah the
other one is not considering the טומאה. tumah. Now of course if
you remove the seven days of נידה niddah you don't have twenty
you have twenty-three so other גרסאות girsos have that it says twenty-three.
Okay but everybody everybody really agrees that a standard period in the
גמרא is assumed to be thirty days. So what defines a woman
as postmenopausal? That she has gone ninety days without bleeding and she
looks older that people will sort of call her grandma she looks
at that age and therefore she's assumed to be postmenopausal and מסולקת
דמים mesuleket damim to continue.